Okay. And our meeting is being recorded.
Hello and good afternoon everyone. My
name is Dr. Dominic Zerlo and I'd like
to welcome you to our second listening
session for the medical psilocybin
program. Thank you for being here. By
registering and joining in this virtual
setting, you are agreeing to be recorded
and for the recording to be made public.
If you do not agree, you may log off the
meeting at this time.
And again, I am Dr. Dominic Zerlo and I
am the director for the New Mexico
Department of Health Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin.
Joining me from the department today is
Brenda Martinez, deputy director for the
Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin,
Rosalie Nava, our health education
programmer program manager. Carmen
Batista, Katie Fryag, and Adrien
Estrada, our health education team for
the center. Jonathan Musher, management
analyst, Raymond Gagos, systems and data
analyst, and Kathy Audiri, our IT
project manager.
As an update for the program, as many of
you probably know, Senate Bill 219, the
Medical Psilocybin Act, was passed by
the New Mexico State Legislature and
signed into law by Governor Luhan Gisham
this past spring. The statute took
effect on June 20th, 2025, and it
requires the Department of Health to
stand up the program by December 31st,
2027.
Currently, the program is working with
both the office of the governor and the
office of the secretary of health to
assemble the medical psilocybin advisory
board. This process should result in the
board being seated in September as
previously announced. Once it is seated,
there will be several additional uh
public meetings and listening sessions
scheduled. Some of these will be
conducted in person and some will be
virtual or hybrid.
And by hybrid we mean they will be in
person with virtual options.
The initial primary purpose of the board
is to create review and recommend rules,
regulations and protocols for the
structure and management of the program
to the secretary of health. With this in
mind, the specifics such as what lensure
will be required, types of training and
educational curriculum will be needed,
requirements for cultivators, and
protocols for treatment have not yet
been determined. This and future
listening sessions are one way the board
members and the program hear thoughts,
ideas, and concerns from the different
community members who are or who may be
involved in the program.
As a reminder, this is being recorded
and the recordings will be made public
on the program website. Um, please see
the screen for the link to the program
website as well as the program email.
Please remember to refrain from using
profanity or inappropriate language when
speaking as minors may watch this
recording in the future and
inappropriate language or background may
result in the recording not being able
to be made available to the public
during the listening session. If you
would like to speak, please raise your
hand. If you are on a computer, please
use the hand icon near the top of the
team's window. It says raise just under
the hand icon. If on the team's app on a
phone, please press the ellipses, the
three dots that are in the menu and then
the hand icon will appear and you can
select it. If you're joining through
voice only on a telephone, please press
star five to raise or lower your hand.
Once you have been selected, uh, your
name will be called and you will be able
to unmute. To unmute or mute on Teams on
a computer or on a Teams phone app,
please click on the microphone icon. If
you are joining by telephone, on voice
only, please press star six to unmute or
mute. We will go through the list of
people who wish to speak in the order
people raise their hand. We will take
comments from as many individuals as
possible within the time allotted, which
is until 4:30 p.m. Mountain time today.
Each individual will have up to 3
minutes to speak.
When it is your turn to speak, your name
will be announced as it appears in the
meeting, and you will be able to unmute
yourself at that time. If you are
joining uh again on a computer or on the
team's phone app, simply click on the
microphone icon uh to be able to unmute
yourself. And if by telephone and voice
only, please press star six to unmute or
mute yourself.
When you start speaking, please state
for the record your full name and if you
are here representing yourself or if
representing an organization or company,
which organization or company you are
representing. You may then make your
statement. There will be a notification
provided to help you complete your
statement when 30 seconds remain in your
time. At 3 minutes, your microphone will
be muted.
If at the end of the list of people who
would like to speak, there is still
time. Anyone wishing to speak a second
time will be provided with an
opportunity to raise their hands again.
And again, the listening session will
end at 4:30. So, we will stay on the
line until 4:30 regardless of uh the
number of people who are speaking. And
if there are more individuals who would
like to speak than time permits, we
encourage you to join other listening
sessions as they are scheduled.
Future public meetings and listening
sessions will be announced on the
program website.
In addition, we do now have a way to
sign up for updates and I will go
through that in just a moment. However,
if you also wish to provide a written
statement, there will be options to do
so at a later time after the board has
been seated.
Please remember this is a listening
session and the program will not be
answering questions at this time.
However, we will take the information
and questions that may be posed during
this session and an FAQ will be
published soon with information from
this session and from the previous
listening sessions.
The recordings from this listening
session and the previous listening
session will be posted to the website
once they have been reviewed to ensure
there is no inappropriate language that
is included on it.
At this point in time, I will go through
the steps for how to sign up for updates
regarding the program.
The first step would be to visit
www.nmhealth.org.
Once you do so, in the upper right hand
corner, there is uh a link where you can
click to sign up for e news.
Once you click on that link, you will be
taken to a page which requests your
email address, first and last name and
your physical address.
Complete those areas and then the next
step will be to complete or click on the
link for medical psilocybin program.
Once you do that, at the bottom of the
page, simply click sign up and you may
be asked to confirm if you are a robot
uh or not a robot, I should say. So,
please make sure to confirm you are not
a robot. And at that point, you will be
signed up for our e updates.
This information, the link to click and
uh sign up for this is also currently on
our program website. So if you're
familiar with our website, you can go
there and join through that pro through
this process. I will repeat this
information towards the end of the
presentation or I'm sorry towards the
end of the session and uh so that people
have it and are able to go through that
process.
At this time we are ready to start
hearing from individuals. And so again,
if you are on a computer and you would
like to speak, please click on the raise
your hand icon.
Uh if you are uh interested in speaking
and you are on your phone on the team's
app, please click on the three ellipses
in the menu and then the hand icon will
appear for you to select it. And if you
are joining through voice only, please
press star five.
Okay, we do have a number of um of
folks. Again, we'll be calling on you in
order
uh of your raised hand. The first person
is Andrew uh Constantine.
Um Andrew, please go ahead and unmute
your line. You have three minutes.
If you're speaking, your line is still
muted. Please press star six or hit the
microphone button.
Hey, Andrew, we're not able to hear you,
so I'm going to go ahead and um mute
your line. We'll come back to you.
Next up is Jim Dodson.
Jim, please unmute your line. You have
three minutes.
>> I am Jim Dodson, a qualified candidate
seeking the important role of patient
advocate on the MPP advisory board.
Treatmentresistant PTSD patients are
forced to suffer, resulting in lost
jobs, lost lives, and lost souls,
leaving a legacy of despair for future
generations to bear. Obviously, the
medical psilocybin
is the path forward for these desperate
patients. At long last, a promising
viable alternative treatment is coming.
Speaking as an informed patient
advocate, these vulnerable patients
require easy, affordable, local access
to like-minded facilitators
and protection from any unauthorized
misappropriation of this powerful sacred
medicine.
It is a gift of new life too precious
for profiteering.
Speaking as a prospective facilitator, I
want to be trained to help others like
me in my small township. I'm not seeking
a career. I'm a volunteer supporting
right to act right to try act elderly
patients for example on low incomes
seeking relief at the end of days the
equity fund must invest in improving the
lives of our marginalized citizens
once the success of this program bears
good fruit and it will the return on
investment will become a golden asset
for our collective well-being
I'm not a healer the medicine does all
the heavy lifting
Maria Sabina is my source for ceremony
and courage
as a servant to the patient guiding and
guarding over them during their journey.
I rem I recommend that all patients seek
deeper ongoing integration by referring
them to like-minded therapists creating
a dynamic circle of healing counterparts
in collaboration. Imagine our state
arassing erasing trauma from every
township one facilitator at a time.
harvesting a bountiful surplus of
successful outcomes. Finally, easy,
affordable access to medicine for all
authorized patients. A patient develops
a personal relationship with the
medicine that saves them from
themselves.
Micro doing or occasional intentional
use is desired outcome for perpetuating
wellness in these now knowledgeable
patients.
They are become fully becoming fully
capable of self-regulation by becoming
whole.
>> And a healed patient has the potential
to become an effective community
resource perhaps even as a facilitator.
Imagine that.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Um, okay. Andrew, we're going to try
your uh your line again.
Your mute has been
uh your microphone has been activated.
Please unmute your line.
You have three minutes.
>> All righty. Sorry about that. I was
having issues with uh that. Uh my name
is Andrew Constantine. I'm speaking as a
student and as a part of the Blue Morpho
Academy in Mikas, Peru. Um, I wanted to
come on here to advocate for,
how do I say this? Um, the the
preservation and the integration of the
traditional lineages that we're trying
to integrate into our western society.
We there's um there's not a um there's
no standardization at the moment for any
psychedelic spiritual practices. And
this is something that the Blue Morpho
Academy is trying to bring. um and also
into this new emerging culture that
we're all kind of finding ourselves in.
The main thing that I wanted to just say
was
preserve um preserving and integrating
the traditional lineages into this this
new way of how we're trying to work with
medicine is something that I think is
going to be really important for us to
get the kind of results that we're
really wanting. Um, and um, I uh I think
that's that's all I wanted to say. I'm
just so glad to be here and listening to
what everyone else has to say. So, uh,
thank you so much.
Okay, next we will go to uh, Dan
Hassen Hen. Dan, your line should be um
able to be unmuted. You have three
minutes.
>> Hi there.
>> Hello.
>> Hello. My name is Daniel Houston. I'm
from the wonderful state of Oregon. Uh I
am the only licensed uh and approved
psilocybin testing laboratory in the
state of Oregon. There used to be two of
us. Um, I'm here to offer my uh insight
into the industry and to help anybody
with anything they need. I do not plan
on opening up there in Colorado, but I
want to help regulators. I want to help
people understand what is broken here in
Oregon and what is really the problem uh
happening up here. Um currently it is
not feasible for people to be doing
treatments treatments over time and we
have tons of data. Uh originally in the
beginning went from higher doses now
they're more lower doses and um
businesses are not uh sustainable. We're
losing businesses all the time.
Currently, uh, year to date, I'm nine
months into this year of testing for the
legal market and, uh, I've only done
$17,000 in total sales in order to help,
uh, the laboratory, whoever decides to
open up in C in uh, Nevada. Um, I really
encourage the regulators to allow them
to
um, test for anybody that is interested
in having mushrooms tested to allow them
to be able to financially afford what is
going on uh, or what is happening in the
industry. It is such a small industry.
There's such so many um, regulations,
the costs and everything involved in it.
Again, I just want to help. Uh, I put my
phone number or my ad email address in
the chat, Rose City Laboratories,
Portland, Oregon. I'd love just to talk
and tell everybody what's happening,
what's good and what's not. Um, I'm
really excited to see you guys u with
these listening sessions and everything
that's going on. And I just really am
excited to see a third state come
online. Um again, um I Oregon is
currently on in the process of possibly
um closing up shop and uh stopping our
silicide program because it's not
sustainable with the fees, not
sustainable with the revenue
requirements of only
>> not sustainable with the only
requirements of only being able to test
within the industry and so on and so
forth. Um, I just wish you guys all
well. Congratulations.
I'm I'm I'm available if you need me.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Next, we will go to uh Kevin
Lenberg. Should apologize in advance if
I if I mess up any names, so forgive me
in in advance. Uh Kevin, your line is
unmuted. You have three minutes.
>> You were very close. Lenn.
>> Lenn. Thank you.
>> You You got it. So, I'm Kevin Lennberg.
I'm the policy director for the patient
advocacy nonprofit Clusterbusters and
the executive director of the
Psychedelics and Pain Association. One
in five Americans suffers from a chronic
pain disorder. And for the four
conditions that are listed in the New
Mexico Medicals psilocybin Act, all of
them are associated with significantly
higher rates of chronic pain. A growing
body of research, both clinical trials
and patient surveys, shows that people
living with pain conditions, including
cluster headache, migraine,
fibromyalgia, low back pain, traumatic
brain injuries, and more, find effective
and enduring relief with the therapeutic
use of psilocybin. The protocols of
psilocybin for chronic pain are often
different from those commonly used for
mental health conditions, frequently
involving lower dose amounts and
multiple treatments. As you design the
medical psilocybin program, we have a
number of asks that we hope you will
consider. Number one, ensure that all
facilitators receive training in the use
of psilocybin for chronic pain. Many of
the people they treat will be suffering
with pain in addition to other
qualifying conditions. End of life care
is one of the conditions mentioned in
the legislation and pain management is a
core component of hospice care. Number
two, as quickly as possible, add chronic
pain as one of the qualifying conditions
to access psilocybin. The data
supporting psilocybin for a wide range
of chronic pain conditions is robust and
there is tremendous patient need for
more effective therapies. Number three,
create flexible regulations allowing for
the full range of therapeutic doses and
frequencies of use that are best for a
wide range of conditions. And last,
number four, explore responsible
policies that will enable home use of
psilocybin under the supervision of
facilitators.
Large doses of psilocybin with the
mental health support of a present
facilitator is just one of many methods
of using psilocybin. Like how doctors
can prescribe medicines for home use,
facilitators should be able to authorize
appropriate doses of psilocybin for
qualified patients to use on their own.
People with cluster headache most
commonly use low doses of psilocybin
about a gram of dried mushroom and they
take it multiple times each spread 5
days apart and research shows that more
than half of real world use of
psilocybin involves more frequent micro
doing neither of these types of use work
only model
>> people with pain are increasingly using
and reporting remarkable healing with
psilocybin New Mexico has an incredible
opportunity to reduce suffering uffing
and improve health by including chronic
pain as a qualifying condition and
allowing responsible legal access to
therapeutic home use of micro and low
doses of psilocybin. Thank you for
listening.
>> Thank you Kevin.
>> Okay, next we go to Ann Hamilton.
Ann, please unmute your line. You have
three minutes.
And I see your line is still muted. If
you're having difficulty, reminders is
to click the the mic. There you go.
Thank you.
>> Hear me? Amazing. Hi everybody. Amazing.
Um thank you for hosting. Um, my name is
Anne Hamilton and I'm the founder and
executive director of the survivorship
collective. We're the first nonprofit
that designs and facilitates
trauma-informed psilocybin group
retreats for the oncology community and
also end of life care. We've been
working in Oregon and we'll probably be
working in Colorado soon. And I just
wanted to say thank you for um for
making this possibly available in um New
Mexico for our community. Uh, I know
that this is already like a train that's
moving, but one thing that we've been
able to offer our community is group
retreats and it makes it more
accessible. Um, it makes it less
expensive. Um, and it's also something
that is evolving in a very kind of
organic way through community-led
efforts. So um as much as we are very
grateful for and definitely need medical
um expertise where it comes to paliative
care and oncology care, we also
definitely need um actual participants
and actual patients saying what they
need because there's a lot of experts in
the field but not enough voices from the
actual people who need it. Um and so I
just wanted to say if you ever need any
any help or or guidance, we have an
amazing group of of people. um who are
you know metastatic patients but also
have a lot of um life in them and time
uh who would love to talk about how to
how to serve that community best because
there definitely needs to be more
patient voices um as well as expert
voices. So thank you so much. That's all
I have to say.
>> Thank you an
>> okay next we'll go to Trina Zer. Trina,
your line. Please unmute your line. You
have three minutes.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> All right. Thank you. My name is Trina
Zaylor. I'm a licensed clinical social
worker and I've worked in hospice and
paliotative care for the past 10 years.
I have four suggestions that I'd like to
make for the board today. Uh the first
is regarding the end of life care
qualifying condition. Uh I ask that we
resist any temptation to define
qualification based on a prognostic
prognostic time frame and instead we
consider a broader paliotative care
definition that would include anyone
with a lifelimiting serious illness
regardless of hospice eligibility or
specific prognosis. I've witnessed end
of life anxiety keeping people from
having conversations well upstream um
while they are still healthy enough to
do so. And we often see that anxiety
keep people from accepting hospice care
until they're within the last few days
of life. My hope is that by giving
people this essential time and space um
to they can fully benefit from the p
from the treatment and be fully present
to make uh these future treatment
decisions as they move in their illness.
My second suggestion is to consider
inclusion of the daily support person in
treatment. We witness up close how the
anxiety of the support system informs
and exacerbates anxiety in the patient.
And by including the support person, my
hope is that this would further support
the person with serious illness and
reduce reduce the risk of complicated
grief for the the daily support person
after death. My third suggestion is for
the treatment protocol to include a
protocol for micro doing. Uh this could
be based on established protocols that
already exist. um include periodic
integration sessions and especially in
the the realm of end of life care
thinking of ways on how to uh reduce the
anxiety about the treatment itself and
um familiarize people with the
experience of letting go um that control
I think could be very helpful and then
my fourth suggestion is regarding
clinician training um for this I I I'm
hoping that the board will create a
lensure process
um similar to what we see for social
work. Uh one in which a variety of
training programs across the country uh
are accepted as an initial uh basis for
being a clinician. Um second, you know,
perhaps including a threshold
requirement for hours, you know, among
those programs.
>> You have 30 seconds remaining. and most
importantly including a New Mexico
specific class on the rules and ethics
and cultural considerations of
psilocybin uh assisted treatment here in
this state. Um with that be able to
provide a source of um lenture for
people to practice this. Thank you so
much.
>> Thank you Trina.
Next we go to um to Paul Walton. Paul,
please unmute your line. You have three
minutes.
>> Hi, can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> My name is Paul Walton and I want to
thank you first for the opportunity to
speak and this is a great opportunity
for New Mexico to lead in policy uh that
is safe and that is reachable for all
those in need. Um, I'm with Firefighters
for Plant Medicine and I've been a
firefighter New Mexico for over 17
years. As a firefighter, I've witnessed
and experienced firsthand the physical
and emotional toll that rules uh can
impose on individuals. Our work often
involves exposure to traumatic events
that can lead to several work-related
injuries, PTSD being just one of them,
also pain, sleeping disorder, anxiety,
um, to name a few others. Yet, first
responders are often overlooked when it
comes to mental health treatment. Uh to
clarify, first responders are not just
firefighters, law enforcement, or EMS,
but also corrections, dispatch, and
emergency room staff as well. Uh these
work-related PTSD symptoms often make
normal everyday life a struggle for
first responders. These struggles not
only affect first responders, but their
families and everyone around them.
Unfortunately, first responders are
often the last to seek help due to
cultural stigmas surrounding mental
health. Ask a first responder how they
feel. Even on their worst day, they will
tell you they are fine. Um, this along
with affordability presents treatment
barriers for first responders. How do we
make it affordable for first responders?
A couple ideas and maybe have a New
Mexico state equity fund that would
relieve some of the cost for treatments
or possibly some kind of reward system
for those uh that are willing to treat
first responders in a reduced rate. Um,
and how do we solve the stigma? As first
responders uh cannot show emotion, they
must uh carry that trauma with them
without looking weak and be in control
of the situation. So these are barriers
and in order to treat these public
servants, we must f reach them and break
down these treatment barriers. First
responders are not your normal health
patient and need special attention for
effective treatment. This could be
achieved with special treatment
protocols for therapists treating first
responders. I've talked with numerous
first responders and a lot would be
comfort would not be comfortable in a
clinical or group setting for an
experience. So, I feel like making the
settings um and accommodating patients
with special needs and comfort levels um
would be a great benefit uh when
deciding on these regulations. Another
tool to address treatment barriers would
be micro doing. As mentioned before,
having a micro dose treatment regulation
uh could help those that are
uncomfortable going right into
>> 30 seconds remaining
>> going right into a macro or therapeutic
dose. This would help the first
responder patient open up and soften
those emotional and control barriers
they had built up for years. I would
love to help advise uh the Department of
Health in any policy and regulation
rules related to first responders. And I
hope that the New Mexico Department of
Health will look at these barriers for
first responders seriously and find a
way to work with adviserss and to find
solutions to help our f public servants.
When our first responders are healthier,
their families, co-workers, employers
benefit and the communities directly
benefit health.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Paul.
>> Thanks.
Okay, next we go to Joshua
Kappell Capel.
Remember that apology I gave earlier.
Joshua, please unmute your line.
>> Hi, thank you. It's Joshua Kapp and
thank you very much. Um, you know, and I
just want to give a a thanks to the New
Mexico Health Department for having this
listening session. It's really important
um you know to obtain public feedback
you know to develop a really inclusive
and safe program. My name is Joshua
Kappa. I'm an attorney licensed in
Colorado. I was one of the main drafters
for the Colorado Natural Medicine Health
Act. I chair the campaign committee and
I currently serve as the senior policy
director for the healing advocacy fund
in addition to representing private
clients through my law team at Facete.
New Mexico is now the third state to
create access to psychedelic care.
Similar to how Colorado had the
opportunity to build off of Oregon, New
Mexico had the opportunity to build off
of both Colorado and Oregon and truly
create a model program for future
states. In Colorado, we've been focusing
on affordability, inclusivity, and
safety. We've made large steps forward,
but yet more could still be done to
ensure that every adult who needs
medical access to psilocybin care
receives it at a price point they can
afford and in a setting they feel safe
and comfortable. This is where the
opportunity lies in New Mexico.
Ultimately, if we're looking to increase
affordability, we need smart
regulations. Regulations that protect
public from harm and are not overly
burdensome to that increase the cost of
services. A couple thoughts around, you
know, a couple thoughts around
affordability. One, group sessions. It
goes without saying that group sessions,
you know, will help on affordability.
Um, number two, separate roles of care.
Having different um licensed
professionals and different roles of
care could help lower costs. um you know
by having more expensive medical
professionals at the screening phase and
less expensive um facilitators or
traditional healers in the facilitation
phase and hopefully you know having an
inclusive um definition of a clinician
to include those who've been practicing
with these medicines working with the
medical provider um would be also
helpful in lowering the cost of of care
and increasing um inclusivity. Another
sort of piece is expanding the
definition of clinician to include
health care providers that are also
entities in in addition to health care
providers that are individuals. And this
could also, you know, allow for a
broader range of um members on a team to
provide care and address, you know, an
issue that has come up with DEA
registrations. Um, another potential way
to reduce care is is having flexible
locations is trusting um the medical
providers and the care teams to provide
psilocybin care in places that they feel
are safe and comfortable and not require
overly burdened regulations. And
finally, you know, and I'll talk more if
there's more time later, but I do want
to say one of the biggest things we miss
in Colorado is excluding pain patients
and those who take lowd do psychedelics
instead of SSRIs or who micro dose. and
in New Mexico, you know, that you know,
there is opportunity to expand the
definition of medical services to
include these modalities of care that
don't involve direct um that don't
involve direct physical supervision, but
more of an oversight model. And this
would really
>> Your time is up.
>> Greatly increase um the inclusivity of
this program. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, Joshua.
[Music]
Okay, next we go to Amy. Uh Amy has no
last name displayed. Amy, please unmute
your line.
As a reminder, you can press the mic
icon or press star six on your phone.
Amy, please unmute your line.
Okay, Amy may be having some difficulty
unmuting. We'll come back to her.
Um, next is Wendy Jean Lindscott.
Wendy, please unmute your line.
>> Can you hear me? Can you hear me?
>> We can. You have three minutes.
>> Excellent. Thank you so much, Kathy and
Dominic. We are grateful for this
opportunity. Nice to see you again,
Dominic. Circling back around a few
years later um after we got the micro
licenses out from my previous proposal.
I'm here as um a CEO of a nanotechnology
company uh that is working on a a
product in um for the state and it is in
alignment with the silocybin program. We
have a
outside working with us on this. What we
have uh Kathy and Dominic and the people
listening are um a mcelium that is uh
has miracle molecules a C6 folery
miracle molecule in it that is a radical
um scavenger AIDS HIV cancer and all
this in our medicine and so that it also
has microinabonoid so our focus has been
on the molecular medicine because our
body and our cells only need what we
need and there's so many um contaminants
that can be taken up in these mushrooms
that are grown and given out to people
that we're not able to test on. So you
may be pulling up uranium and you don't
know that that's what your mushroom is
getting. So we've really been focusing
on the molecular and the healing parts
and u molecules in the um the mushroom
and fungi world. And we're excited about
um the lab that we have created for a
pilot study and we look forward to
advancing our conversations on this
because it includes the public and by
donating our medicines that we're
creating. We are now opening a whole new
world of research on quantum medicine
with um this C60 miracle molecule in our
mcelium. It's also able to be
transferred into our mushroom genetics.
So, we're the first to have it here in
New Mexico. So, we're really excited
about that and advancing our mushroom
medicine molecular
technology and with that um everything
that we've created from this the the
waste is not waste because now we are
able to transfer that 30 seconds on a
monetary thank you on a monetary level
by our waste products being turned into
quantum.note nanotechnology that we get
to work with the state on for interstate
commerce revenue and free treatments for
the people by a fully supported private
funded program. So I look forward to
meeting with you on this and future
discussions with you Dom and Kathy in
the state. This is for everybody and its
treatment and treatment should be free.
So we helped um we helped create
facilitate this and it's a whole
community coming together for this to
happen.
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Wendy.
>> Okay, I see Amy has uh rejoined. So,
Amy, I'm gonna come back to you. Um,
please unmute your line.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, I can.
>> Great. So, thank you for the opportunity
to speak today. My name is Amy Trumper
and I'm currently a graduate counseling
student. I'm not speaking on behalf of
an organization, just as a passionate
community member.
First, I want to acknowledge how hopeful
I feel about the passage of SB219.
This legislation is a landmark for New
Mexico, and I'm grateful for the
Department of Health's leadership in
guiding its implementation. One of the
strongest parts of the bill is a
requirement that psilocybin must be
cultivated here in New Mexico. That
decision ensures that the benefits, both
economic and cultural, stay rooted in
our state. I believe the same principle
should apply to facilitator training.
Training is not just a technical
process. It shapes the values, ethics,
and culture of this entire program. If
we allow outofstate organizations to
come in and set up shop, we risk
outsourcing our framework to entities
that may not share New Mexico's
priorities or cultural context.
We have the talent, the knowledge, and
the community here to build training
programs that are accountable to New
Mexicans. programs that honor our unique
diversity, reflect our local values, and
integrate the voices of nation, tribe,
and public peoples, not just as an
afterthought, but as co-designers.
I recently attended a Colorado-based
training orientation, and when asked
about New Mexico, their response was,
"Oh, yeah, we'll definitely be offering
training there." That gave me pause. I
don't doubt their expertise, but New
Mexico deserves training programs that
are built for and by New Mexicans, just
as cultivation is required to be. If
cultivation must remain local, why
shouldn't facilitation training? Both
are foundational. Both set the tone for
what this program will become, and both
should remain accountable to the
communities who will be most impacted. I
believe New Mexico can build something
not just effective, but deeply rooted
and truly our own. Thank you for
listening and for your leadership.
>> Thank you, Amy.
Okay, next we go to uh James
Brown. James, your mic should be ready.
Please unmute your line.
>> Afternoon everyone. Uh my name is Dr.
James Brown and I am a registered
pharmacist here in New Mexico as well as
a disabled uh foreign war veteran. I
served in the Navy for 8 years for this
great country in this state. Um this is
an amazing time and to echo Amy. Um that
is something that needs to be driven by
New Mexicans for New Mexicans and in a
way that if we had heard this um I am
trained in Oregon as a facilitator
and as a facilitator of psilocybin in
Oregon it's very difficult um it's very
costly access is is not there only for
the very elite uh groups of people and
as you know New Mexico is is not that
way um we need access for every New
Mexican. And so I'm here today to
advocate for that access. Um we need to
propose that every business license um
that is given out um has an equity plan
um attached to it. Um equity is very
important to New Mexico. Um this should
be a requirement and a necessity um to
required to be a license in New Mexico.
Individuals as well as groups. So this
should be a group and individual
setting. uh sentence setting is very
important as you know um as well as um
preparation integration um is is key.
It's the responsibility of the
department of health as well as the
psilocybin board to steward and ensure
that New Mexico medical psilocybin
program is sustainable
and it must be in our mindsets and
thinking of looking at the long-term
benefits
and what are the other consequences. You
know, as a pharmacist, I want to make
sure that everybody is aware that there
is consequences to things that can
happen with this powerful medicine and
there's side effects and I'm here to to
advocate for that and I'd love to
partner with the department of health as
well as the psilocybin board to be that
advocate for those type of interactions,
adverse effects, um drug drug disease
state. These things need to be in
guidelines need to be written as well as
telearm pharmacy. This is a thing that
is huge to New Mexico. We have an
opportunity to use tele pharmacy um to
increase our access in our homes. This
should be used in homes, clinics,
outside, inside. Again, a tele pharmacy
model. The regulations need to have
dose, what type, frequency. And I want
to also propose today a prescription
model. This model would be based off of
other based medical current guidelines,
policies, procedures that are already in
place. Um, a prescription based model
will allow us to use and protect New
Mexicans. Um, as you're aware, this
would also be a help with DRG billing
coding. Um, as you well know, Medicare,
Medicaid are the primary payer for this
state. And so, we need to find access
that way. And so, create a DRG code
using prescription-based models. Um,
again, thank you for your time and
everybody's space today. I do appreciate
you.
>> Thank you, James.
Okay, next we go to Stuart Anderson.
Please unmute your line.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, I can.
>> Great. Um, well, thank you so much for
doing this and and there are definitely
people much more uh versed in silicon
than myself that are on this call
because I know some of them. I am a
primary care doctor and and also a
ketamine provider here in Santa Fe. And
so I just wanted to say I think that the
the way that uh so there are things that
are advantageous about or that we can
look to as the way that we provide
ketamine for patients for chronic pain,
substance abuse, depression, PTSD
um and for end of life um angst uh or
end of life anxiety, excuse me. um uh
which uh and so opening up using
psilocybin for all of those I think can
be could be really fantastic. Some of
the some of the challenges with ketamine
therapy are one it's not covered by any
insurance Medicare or Medicaid uh and
cost can become quite an issue. So we
look to doing group sessions. Socon is
of course a a more challenging
um uh treatment because it's
substantially longer, you know, four to
six hours versus one to two. And so
being able to have prescribers, you
know, be responsible for deciding who uh
is going to actually who who is who is
okay to receive the medicine and then
training uh other um uh other folks to
sit with patients either in the home as
um forgive me I can't remember who the
Pearson was talking. like in hospice,
you know, hospice nurses being able to
sit with people or doing group sessions
um as a way of distributing uh the cost
and making it financially feasible for
businesses here in New Mexico to provide
that care. And I do think you know
there's that question as Dr. Brown was
alluding to of doing tele medicine. You
know there is this you know there are
with ketamine you know during COVID
things sort of exploded with uh Mind
Bloom and Joyful or whatever all these
other um uh outside companies uh just
doing uh tele medicine sessions and
prescribing relatively large doses of
ketamine with very little oversight. And
I don't I on the one hand we have a very
remote state and we want to make that
access available but
>> you have 30 seconds remaining regulated
much and so I think keeping doing that
in a better fashion would be beneficial
for our patients here in the state. So
thank you for your time and I'm so
excited that New Mexico is making this
move. Thank you.
>> Thank you Stuart.
>> Okay, next we go to Lisa. Lisa, there's
no last name uh listed for you, so
hopefully there's not more than one um
with their hand up at the moment. Lisa,
please unmute your line.
>> Hello. Uh can you guys hear me?
>> Yes, we can. Thank you.
>> Perfect. Uh hi. Uh thank you so much for
hosting this. My name is Lisa Ginsburg.
I'm the founder of Chunga Institute. Uh
we are state regulated training program
based in Oregon and Colorado. Um I would
like to advocate for
a layer of protection and dual lensure
for facilitators
similar to Colorado model to protect
medical licensed providers due to the
federal status of psilocybin which is
federally illegal and prohibited. uh
licensed medical provider especially
those who can write prescriptions
potentially um can face danger of losing
their license by engaging with federally
legal substance. So um I would like to
urge the state um pay attention to that
and create a layer of protection to make
sure that nurses and all other medical
practitioners will be protected and and
incentivized to engage in this practice.
Um, also I would like to advocate for
open access to education. Um, I think
there are so many brilliant researchers
and clinicians and people that have
hands-on experience from Oregon and
Colorado and actively working with
facilitating
the sessions can add
a tremendous amount of knowledge and
experience to future practitioners and I
think it would be a big missed
opportunity
restricting access to education and
knowledge by uh not allowing from
outside educators to enter the market.
Uh that would be all. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Lisa.
>> Okay, next we go to Chad Lozano. Chad,
please unmute your line.
>> So, can you all hear me?
>> We can.
>> Okay. Um hello everyone. Dr. Zer, hello.
Good hearing you premier. Good seeing
you. Uh a lot of people in here today.
I'm just really um jumping on today to
show support and um really hope that we
can steer this medical school assignment
the right direction. Um and some of you
don't know me. I've been a longtime
medical cannabis and cannabis advocate
here in New Mexico for uh many years
over a decade. Um especially when we
were with the medical cannabis side of
the DO and um who also supported this
little side of stuff, you know, when it
was going down the legislature too. So,
I really hope that we can get something
for New Mexico and learn the lessons
from Oregon and Colorado what not to do.
Um, that's something huge to remember
because as been said many times already
that it's really expensive in a lot of
these states to either operate or just
to be a patient there and we have to
keep in mind that New Mexico is plagued
by say plague, but we are a very large
state. Um, even in the medical cannabis
years, you know, a lot of the patients
had a hard time affording cannabis still
to this day. Um, and that's not going to
change side by side. So, we have to
ensure that even New Mexicans can get,
>> Chad. We may, it appears we may have
lost you.
>> Guys, hear me?
>> Uh, there you go. We can hear you.
>> I was I was coming from the the CCD
hearing, so I'm heading back to Chris,
so I'm on the road. Sorry about that.
Uh, how much time do I have left?
>> 1 minute 30 seconds.
>> Cool. Awesome. Thank you. Um, I don't
know where I stopped off, but I want to
make sure that, you know, um, New
Mexicans get affordable, uh, medical
psilocybin. Um, let's learn from the
mistakes that Oregon and Colorado has
made. Um, let's not do everything that
those states do, but also keep in mind
that we're going to make our own
mistakes and we have to do things the
New Mexican way. Um, there's not one
right way to do this, and it's the way
that's going to work for us. Um, so I
want to make sure that, you know, the
patients are taken care of and also the
fact that New Mexicans can get involved
in this and it's not just the the most
elite New Mexicans with the most money.
Um, I believe that, you know, some of
the best medicines come from the people
who can't always afford the most
expensive licenses. Um, so if we keep
those things in mind, I think this
program will thrive and we can be a
model for the rest of the nation. Um,
but let's just keep those things in mind
and also um learn from the mistakes that
we have from the other markets like in
the medical cannabis program how it was
so limited and so expensive. So, thank
you so much and I'm excited to see where
this goes. Thank you guys.
>> Thank you, Chad.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay, next we go to Jen Clemente. Jen,
please unmute your line.
>> Hi, thanks so much for having me on. My
name is Jen. I live in uh Truth or
Consequences. I volunteer for End of
Life Options New Mexico and I'm also the
uh psychedelic education lead at our
hopefully future service center here in
our little town. Um I I really advocate
for the rigorous uh spirit medicine
preparation and integration and I'm
really excited about the emerging fields
of psychedelic chapency and deathd work.
So um given the breadth of training most
people in this field have already
attained and the financial constraints
that most doulas and chaplain face, I
suggest that the state allow chaplain
and death doulas to complete whichever
facilitator training program they find
most suitable. So as long as they also
pass a single standardized state exam,
that way everyone is held to the same
standard of safety and ethics while
still honoring the diversity of training
paths. To support this, I encourage the
development of a study guide for that
exam. It should cover all the basics
like psilocybin pharmarmacology, trauma
informed and culturally competent care,
end of life applications, crisis
response, ethics and boundaries, and the
specific laws here in New Mexico. The
balance of uh flexibility and
accountability would help ensure safety
while also letting hospice chaplain and
doulas bring their unique gifts into
this important work without enduring
more financial strain.
>> Thank you, Jen.
>> Thank you,
Okay, next we go to Mason Burke. Burks,
my apologies. Mason, please unmute your
line.
>> Hi. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Awesome. One second. All right. So, hi.
My name is Mason Burks and I'm here as
the oper operations coordinator of
AQPSI, which is an opportunity based
harm reduction drug education nonprofit.
Uh I've taken salad a couple of hundred
times and I've been a passive attending
support person for about as many people
and it's from that perspective that I
want to emphasize two main points. Um
the first is not only is there an
immense possibility for the perpetuation
of inequality due to the differential
access and uh you know predatory
insurance industry and licensing
restrictions and all that sort of thing.
Um but uh the efficacy of therapy as a
whole uh is uh dependent on the way in
which someone aligns with the western
conception of like what an individual
what individuality is like the atomized
isolated wrong assumptions that are made
about like what a person is. Um which is
to say the degree to which an individual
conforms to colonial and late capitalist
conceptions of human life that are at
odds with the relational communal ways
that are rooted deeply in our our
biology and our cultural systems and
then the the way that these medicines
work which is to say white people for
the most part. Um and uh so I I advise
on the strongest terms possible the
development of a framework which can
permit the use likely in lower doses
than the breakthrough catalyst doses
used in the literature of psilocybin and
community settings where immersion in
familial and cultural fabric can permit
the healing damage that exists in that
same collective reality. Uh Timothy
Larry was wrong about a whole lot of
things but the limitations of clinical
model are not one of them. Uh number two
uh this program has increased
philosophies. It's not going to has uh I
know this for a fact. uh the
governmental approval of these medicines
even in the abstract dissolves the only
barrier remaining for a great many
people who are already pursuing access
and who may in the end remain excluded
from the designated qualification for
whatever this program turns into and I'm
not referring only to underground
practitioners that have had training but
to people who have no training
whatsoever and for this reason I advise
again in the strongest possible terms
that the program make available a
consumer oriented body of literature
that may permit those pursuing healing
outside of the bounds of officially san
sanctioned spaces to nonetheless ensure
these experiences can remain in line
with the contemporary understanding of
what component of clinical therapy can
or should be carried over into an
informal or personal kind of context. Uh
and just as importantly to review in
clear language what manner of dosing,
involvement, guiding, directing, etc. is
sensitive to a degree that it really
should remain in the in the purview of
highly trained facilitators. Um again,
this isn't enabling illicit use or uh
you know going outside of the law. This
is harm reduction. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mason.
Next we go to Amy Wong Hope. Amy, please
unmute your line.
Hi. Um, so thank you again for this
opportunity for the second listening
session. Um, so I wanted to underscore
what I believe it was Dan Houston said
from Oregon. um far and wide from
talking to lots of folks up in Oregon,
which is where I did my training, they
say that the way the program has been
administered and the rules and
regulations there has really reduced the
amount of facilitators who are seeking
rellicensure and also facilitation
centers are um they're really uh not
financially viable and um also for
jouriers they can't afford to have
multiple journeys when they might need
them for you know really for depression
and and PTSD and substance use. So, what
what many are saying up in Oregon is
that the way that the current market up
there has um been implemented uh in the
in the rules and regulations has really
driven all use underground at this
point. So, this is something very
important for us in New Mexico to
consider that we want to make sure that
we find a way to make sure our rules and
regulations are about safety. I really
loved what Jen Clement said about
possibly having a study guide and uh a
lowcost option for people to get
lensure. My other um point I wanted to
make was to say that there's it looks
like three or four designated psilocybin
advisory board members in certain areas
and certain affinity groups. And I hope
that um the DOH will consider having um
possibly as you know someone who's
knowledgeable about uh predatory
business practices on your board to
protect um the operators in New Mexico
from predatory business practices. um uh
having someone who might be um also a
cultivator and someone who understands
the business of cultivation and what's
gone wrong in other states where um we
know in in the in uh cannabis world um
it really out outpriced uh the local
local cultivators for cannabis and that
became problematic in in many different
states. And so we really want our our
local cultivators to be championed here
because they're really growing medicine
for the people that live here and
there's like that deep connection. So
that's um that's pretty much all I
wanted to say. Thank you so much for
this time.
>> Thank you Amy.
>> Okay, next we go to Cassandra Gurle.
Cassandra, please unmute your line. You
have three minutes.
I see your line is still muted.
Cassandra, press the mic icon to unmute
or press star six from your phone.
Okay, Cassandra, we'll come back to you.
Next, we'll go to Mitchell
Dingel.
Mitchell, please unmute your line.
Hello, my name is Mitch Dingle and I was
present for the first listening session
last month on August 26th. I have been
heavily involved with the medical
cannabis industry in New Mexico since
2017 and it has been a great joy and
honor to have been a part of that
program. I have worked for several
legacy producers. So I implore the
department of health to please be
mindful of the amount of cultivation
licenses issued. I would like to
advocate for a strict cap on these
cultivation or production licenses.
One gram of dried psilocybin is very
very different from 1 g of cannabis
flour. I want to emphasize that again.
There is no need to flood New Mexico
with an overabundance of psilocyum. We
need to emphasize compliance and
adherence to strict guidelines so that
this medicine stays true to the goals
and ethics for this patient centric
program. I am so excited that the
department of health will be overseeing
this as the medical cannabis program was
extremely successful and I am optimistic
that this will follow in the footsteps
of that. That is all. Thank you very
much for your time today.
Thank you, Mitch. Kathy, can we go back
and see if Cassandra uh is able to
unmute?
>> Yes, Cassandra, your line is open.
Please unmute your line.
Cassandra, we do need you to unmute your
line if you would like to speak.
Okay, Cassandra, we will come back to
you. Uh, if you would like to speak,
please go ahead and raise your hand
again. Um and uh Dan just because uh
Daniela Dan Husan uh just because we
want to ensure other people who have not
yet spoken yet uh have the opportunity
we will come back to you. But first I'd
like to open it up and make sure that
anyone who has not yet spoken has the
opportunity. So if you are interested in
speaking please go ahead and raise your
hand here in the team's program. If you
are on a computer or uh or if you are on
a computer, please click on the hand
icon near the top of the team's window
and it says raise under that icon. If
you're on the team's app on a phone, if
you please press on the ellipses, which
are the three dots that are in the menu,
then the hand icon will appear and you
can click on it to raise your hand. If
you are joining through voice only on a
phone, please press star five to raise
or lower your hand.
And we'll give folks a minute or so to
be able to do that just to ensure that
everyone who wishes to speak has the
opportunity. After that, we will go to
anyone who wishes to speak a second
time.
Okay, we do have uh Cassandra has
>> raised your hand again.
>> Yes, has raised hand again.
>> Cassandra, please unmute your line. You
have three minutes.
Okay, Cassandra, we cannot hear you. Um,
we do need you to unmute your line. Uh,
if you are on a computer or on the Teams
app on the phone, you just need to click
on the microphone icon. If you are on
telephone voice only, please press star
six to unmute.
Okay, Cassandra, we will come back to
you is uh just to make sure see if we
can get over the technical issue. Uh in
the meantime, uh seeing that there's no
one else who hasn't spoken yet uh in the
queue, we will go ahead and move forward
to Dan Houston. Kathy, if you will
unmute Dan.
>> Dan, please unmute your line. You have
three minutes.
>> Hello. Thank you again for being able to
speak a second time uh from up here in
Oregon. I wanted to in uh let everybody
know that I heard something earlier
somebody said that once you guys start
talking about regulations this or that
it kind of opens it up and and um people
start consuming or thinking it's um
probably going to be okay and start down
that road. So, I just want to inform
everybody that here in Oregon, there is
a massive issue with black market um uh
or unregulated uh psilocybin quote
unquote psilocybin products on the
market. I actually Rose City
Laboratories, Oregon State University
and Shimatsu big manufacturer of
equipment have a white paper being
published uh in the JAMAMA network,
Journal of American Medicine
Association, and it talks about the um
black market uh psychedelics and what is
actually in them. as a laboratory on the
black market. You can go into any um
pipe shop or smoke shop or um and even
convenience stores and pick these items
up. Inside of these items are things
like um horse tranquilizers. Uh we found
aderall, we found um DMT, we found all
kinds of products in this. It's actually
going to be a big topic hitting the news
and media here in Oregon. uh I can share
the publication with anybody uh after
September 11th. Again, be very very
cautious about the uh black market and
please try to do something about it.
>> Thank you, Dan.
Okay, Cassandra, we're going to come
back to you.
Please unmute your line.
Cassandra, your line is still muted.
I'm not sure if you tried dropping and
rejoining, but sometimes people find
some success with that with when they're
having um difficulty. So, I may suggest
that for you. Um but we're going to go
ahead and call in the next um
the next person.
And that person is Wendy Jane Lindscott.
Wendy, please unmute your line.
Hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Excellent. Thank you so much, Kathy and
Dominic. Um, Cassandra Guter is sitting
next to me. She's having technical
difficulty with her speaker. Even though
she keeps hitting the mic button, for
some reason it's not letting her speak.
So, um, what I wanted to do, uh, thank
you so much, was, uh, speak a little bit
more about, uh, some of the concerns
that people are addressing. The big
thing about having local facilitators
and local people um working from New
Mexico, the people of New Mexico, you
have local healers, medical
practitioners, kunettas that are
facilitators, people have experience
with psilocybin, mushroom and
psychedelic medicines and facilitating
that in a safe um safe um and ethical
environment in hopefully a managed care
setting. And that's what we're focusing
on for the people here because the
people who do live here um who are in
this and interested in this already know
who the black market dealers are. And
I'm going to just tell you, I mean, I'm
not going to mention names, but I
already know who they are, which is one
of the reasons why it has catapulted me
into the molecular medicine to
understand and produce through my
company, Angels of Alchemy, in this lab,
biodnamic safe psilocybin and psilocin
and other molecules from the mushroom
medicine. And it's fully funded and free
for the state and the participants. So
we have the full package that we have
the ability to incorporate and include
the people and the patients of New
Mexico. So it's an integrated system
where the people created the medicine,
the people produce the medicine, the
people test the medicine, the people are
the facilitators. So we're not going to
try and poison each other. So we're the
ones that are creating it. And what it's
going to do is it's going to tick off
the black market because what we're
doing is we're creating a medicine
that's going to be free for the people.
So the black market can't make money off
of it. There goes the black market. So
you're going to know who the black
market people are are because you're
going to have the people who are serious
about their healing involved in the free
silicide program that's able to fund
itself with all the different
disciplines and all the different
practices culturing from death doula to
um pregnancy and and you know bipolar
and Alzheimer's and even AIDS treatment
with what we have in our molecular
medicine.
>> We have 30 seconds remaining.
Thank you, Kathy. So, that's why um I
wanted to speak again and just say we've
looked at all of this. James Brown is a
part of it is a farmd. Um the lab uh
that we're working with is a state lab.
So, we're look looking forward to what
we're bringing and including the
communities of people who are seeking
this and the treatments for their
greater good and the greater good of the
community. So, thank you all so much for
this opportunity. And here we go.
>> Thank you, Wendy.
Okay, I see that Cassandra's raised her
hand again. Uh, Cassandra, please try on
and unmute your line.
>> Yay. Yay. There you go.
So, I was nervous. Thank you guys so
much. So, I'm Cassandra. I work really
hard on the Will you mute yours?
>> On the cannabis program as far as
monitoring it and just checking it out.
Um, there is an echo. Just give me one
second.
Um, I'm really working really hard to
get that um approved. So, I don't know
why there's an echo. Um, but I was
really active on the cannabis side and I
kind of don't want that to happen for
side. I really want it to be more
I don't want it to be
like
I see Wendy's line is muted. Sorry,
Cassandra. Your line is muted.
>> Can you hear me now?
Yes.
>> Okay. So, I just hope that the integrity
of this mushroom uh psilocybin program
stays intact. Um I would hope that it's
more like a therapy based,
clinicalbased. um not necessarily saying
it has to stay in you know um hospitals
or anything like that but I hope that
there is clinician care there is you
know gurinderas there is people around
in a therapeutic setting really having
these doses in a safety um dose setting
you know um like the MD in here said it
could get really um and I'm just going
to straight up and say it it could get
really dangerous um per the doses um per
axis. Um and so clean medicine is really
important. Um access is really
important, dosing is really important
and keeping it ethical, keeping it as a
practitioner um basis and not something
where there's a mushroom clinic on every
um corner of New Mexico. I think that
would be very dangerous to the people of
New Mexico as well as very
um
unmanageable.
So I really hope that when we're
thinking about this program, we're
putting the patients first um rather
than profits. um this is not something
to where people are going to make
millions of dollars, but I hope that it
would help the medical standpoint and
the um mental rehabilitation of the
state. And that's the most important
thing. And if we are overdosing, if we
are overprescribing,
that is going to do the complete
opposite of what this program is trying
to do. So, I hope and pray that
everybody takes doses into consideration
and mental health into consideration
because that's mainly what this program
is for. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Cassandra. And thank you for
bearing with us uh to be able to get you
to be to be able to speak.
>> Thank you so much, guys.
Okay, next we go back to uh Joshua.
Joshua, please unmute your line.
>> Thank you and thank you very much for
the opportunity to to speak again. Um
you know just to build off of you know
some earlier comments around um you know
the black market or the private market.
I do think like one of the big reasons
to create an inclusive program is to you
know is to provide people an opportunity
to participate in the regulated sphere
and by creating a system that brings in
traditional or legacy healers and
provides them a way to participate
actually gives them a path to be
licensed and to be and to be in the
system otherwise they'll continue to do
what they've been doing for 20 years and
they probably have done a lot of good
work in those 20 years. Um, you know,
likewise, you know, creating a system
that allows for um lowd dose
psychedelics at home for pain or or
micro doing, you know, through sort of
like the definition of medical services
also creates a more inclusive program.
And and by create giving people
access and pathways, you know, to do
things legally, you know, it will it's
not going to eliminate, but it will help
to minimize, you know, the the dangers
of the private market. Um, a couple
other pieces I just wanted to say
around, you know, things to think about,
you know, around affordability. You
know, one is, you know, just like an
encouragement to try and figure out how
do we um allow for Medicaid coding for
preparation or integration sessions or
follow on integration sessions and is
there any way to get state Medicaid
dollars in there? And I think that's
something that's really worth exploring.
um you know as it relates to um safety
you know I think the biggest safety
piece is you know is the actual provider
of the medicine it's the safety screens
it's the the clinician the facilitator
and making sure that training is
adequately tailored to them and making
sure that they have appropriate training
that allows them to really address all
the potential harms and all the
potential situations as they provide
this care. also making sure that that
training is uniquely tailored. You know,
you know, it's not helpful for people to
engage in duplicative training. It's
it's actually kind of a burden for
people to participate in this program.
And so having uniquely tailored training
for specific professionals,
you know, would go a long way um in
safety. And then the final piece on
safety, you just making sure that we
have good outcome reporting. you know,
this is a very um new, you know, from a
regulated standpoint, this is a very new
modality of care and we don't know what
sort of contraindications might be um
happening, you know, you yeah, we just
don't know a lot. We know we do know a
lot, but we also don't know a lot. So
just you know good outcome reporting
around adverse events, good outcome
reporting around the benefits and
efficacy of these programs I think will
will go a long way and um allowing us to
adjust the program to increase safety
and increase efficacy. So you know thank
you um all very much for your time.
>> Thank you Josh. And uh just because we
do have uh at least one individual on
the list who has not yet spoken and we
do want to hear from as many people as
possible. Um we're going to go a little
bit out of order for a moment. Uh and go
to Brandon Johnson. Um Brandon Kathy
will unmute you in a moment. Actually,
you are unmuted. You can unmute your
line at this time. Brandon.
>> Hello. My name is Brandon Johnson. Um I
just wanted to jump on here and say
thank you first of all. Um it's really
beautiful to hear this conversation and
be a part of this. Uh one of the first
uh people that spoke talked about
somebody working with this medicine and
coming full circle to be able to be a
supporter for the community. And I just
wanted to say as an advocate for the
medicine over a year and a half ago, I
was an alcoholic
and in a really really difficult place
in my life. Um and this medicine having
to go out of country um and then coming
back and working underground. I was able
to get past that addiction a year and a
half ago and now I can be a really
strong support for the community. So,
I'm really excited that this is going to
become more accessible for the people of
New Mexico and um yeah, it's just an
incredible opportunity for individual
healing and community healing. So, thank
you so much.
>> Thank you, Brandon. And again, just so
that we are able to hear from everyone
at least once who wanted to speak, we
will jump to Dr. Samuel Nez. Uh Dr. Nez,
if you will unmute your line, you are
ready to speak.
>> Hi there. Thank you. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Perfect. Uh, so my name is Dr. Samuel
Nez. I'm actually a practitioner of
Kurandismo. Um, so as New Mexico
implements this medical psilocybin act
and the program, I think it's important
to uh remember that New Mexico has
recognized traditional healers through
the unlicensed healthcare uh practice
act. So there's guranderos, there's
guranderas, medicine people and
traditional heresies, healers that carry
uh generational knowledge that are
trusted by the communities in Colorado.
I've already seen the difficulties with
the accessibility when it comes to the
traditional healers that weren't
included. These communities have deep
ties to the sacred medicines and they're
often the ones that are left out or
pushed to the margins.
So in enacting this uh program, I think
it's important to have a legacy pathway
that recognizes traditional healers.
Otherwise, all we're doing is creating a
a system that privileges only western
clinical providers and sidelining the
very people in which this medicine was
safeguarded. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Samuel.
Okay, next we'll go to Mason Burks.
Mason, please unmute your line.
>> Hi, can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Awesome. Thank you again for the
opportunity to speak a second time. Um,
I briefly wanted to address a couple
things that been said previously by the
attendees, but I promise I'm circling
back to comment directly to Ed Yall. Um,
I just wanted to point out that um, you
know, the conflation of the black market
with like what you might call unethical
actors, people who are only concerned
with profit is is an artifact of some
uh,
you know, discourse around the drug war
that is that is predicated on false
assumptions. Uh, and in our discussion
around you know and this this is not at
all to uh to to devalue or or uh, you
know, decenter the the long longstanding
centuries long traditions of of abuse in
traditional capacities. But when we talk
about traditional uh you traditional
practices or legacy uh practitioners
that that does include the the black
market you know uh I'm sure there are
many many people on this call who are uh
involved in psychedelic medicine and
advocating for it because they've had
really deeply impactful personal
experiences and those those experiences
all happen because of black market right
no one was illicitly producing this
until very recently and uh just speaking
from the experience of uh multi for for
for many years in a harm reduction
capacity I' I've worked closely with
like part of my job has been creating
relationships with people who sell drugs
for the purpose of ensuring that the
drug supply that is available to people
remains uh you know as unadulterated and
and reliable as possible because uh
especially psilocybin I can just say
from having conversations with people
who sell drugs for a living psilocybin
is not something people make very much
money off of and many many many of the
people who are what you would call a
drug dealer or someone who's you know on
the corner uh selling psilocybin to
people uh those people are doing it for
the exact same reason everyone is here
which is a commitment to the the belief
that this is something that people
should have access to. Um and uh I guess
uh you know elaborating on the point of
of uh making sure that the supply that
people have whether they're in in a
clinic or in their living room with
their friend or their college roommate
or something uh is is a safe thing. Um
New Mexico does have access to and does
have a a growing actively growing uh
program for adultering for drugs. Um
there's there's an a furer transformed
mass spectroscopy machine at New Mexico
Haruction Collaborative in Albuquerque.
There's also one at the Mountain Center
in Espanola and there's one somewhere in
Los Cruus. I'm not sure off the top of
my head where. Um but we do have an
existing uh free uh you know anonymous
and uh pretty you know as accessible as
anything could be sort of programmed for
>> developing actively in the state. Um at
present uh the ability to screen
>> thank you. At present the ability to
screen for organic substances is kind of
uh obstructed um just by the
complications of having 1900 different
compounds in an organic sample versus
hey molecule. Um but there's technology
being actively developed also by
companies in New Mexico for for the
ability to screen that sort of thing. So
um we've got a developing infrastructure
for people who are utilizing this
outside of formal capacity to ensure the
safety of those substances. Thank you.
Thank you, Mason.
>> Okay. Uh, we've got one more and I think
that's about all we have time for. Um,
Paul, please unmute your line.
>> Hi, thanks for uh giving me the
opportunity to speak a little bit more
again. Um, I just wanted to bring up one
thing that really hasn't been discussed
and talked about. Um, I think I haven't
heard it really in any other different
programs either. Um, and I think that
Department of Health could really
benefit from having some kind of
training program that addresses law
enforcement and EMS and how to deal with
not only uh, psilocybin now that we're
going to be uh, doing this and there
possibly could be home um, settings and
different things like that, but then
also cannabis as well. and just having
an education on how to address people,
how to talk to people um and how to um
deal with people that are possibly
having um some kind of a bad experience
versus a medical experience. And I think
it would really benefit to have um some
kind of layout and some kind of
education that would help with emergency
care in these situations. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Paul. Uh and at this point in
time we are uh just a couple of minutes
from the end of our session. And so what
I did want to go ahead and do is uh
repeat the information we had said in
the very beginning with regard to uh our
program website. So our program
information the email is
medical.silocybin
dooh.n.gov
and our website is www.nmhealth.org.
org/about
slashmcpp
slash and both of those are on the
screen right now. Um, and then the other
uh item I just wanted to let everyone
know is we do have a method now for
people to sign up for updates and uh to
do so all individuals need to do is go
to www.nmhealth.org
or and from there in the upper right
hand side of the screen uh click on the
sign up for e-news.
Uh once you have done that it will take
you to a page which had requests some
information essentially your email
address first and last name and your
physical address. Once you complete
those, then just simply click on the
medical psilocybin program box and that
will sign you up for updates with regard
to medical psilocybin. I should mention
you are also welcome to sign up for any
of the other categories that are listed
on this page. Uh you can sign up for
multiple categories at the same time.
You don't have to revisit the page each
time.
Uh once you actually have clicked on the
categories that you're interested in,
then just click sign up and depending
upon your uh system in your computer or
your phone, you may then need to confirm
that you are not a robot and then click
continue. Um and so basically that is
just how to sign up for updates. Once
you have done that, you can then uh you
will then receive updates for future
meetings, additional meetings and just
general updates on the program as we
release them. So at this time I would
like to thank you all for joining us
tonight. We do not at this point have
additional listening sessions scheduled
because we are anticipating the board to
be seated uh the medical psilocybin
advisory board that is to be seated
later this month and once it is then we
will set up additional uh listening
sessions andor public meetings with the
board. Uh in the meantime thank you all
very much. This concludes today's
listening session and thank you for
participating and staying until the very
end. For those 33 additional people who
did stay, thank you very much. We
appreciate you and we appreciate the
information, the feedback back, the
comments and the concerns. I hope you
all have a great and wonderful day and
we will see you all again soon
hopefully.